Finding Aid for Mark T. Warner Papers, 1813-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mark T. Warner papers 1813-1974, 1916-1974
Warner, Mark T. (Mark Thomas), 1889-1975.
3 linear feet
93311 Aa 2
Colorado clergyman, proponent of the creation of the Black Canyon of the Gunnison River as a national monument, U.S. Army chaplain during World War II. Correspondence with family members while serving as chaplain during World War II, also other documents from his military service, including programs from services he performed during the war; papers accumulated from his career as Presbyterian minister in Colorado, especially notes from sermons; scattered papers of other, earlier family members; and Black Canyon Monument series which includes correspondence, blueprints and landscaping designs, clippings, and various publications; files relating to research and writing of book about Black Canyon; and photographs and postcards of the area.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Robert M. Warner (donor no. 3808 ), 1991.
The collection is open to research.
Mark Thomas Warner was born February 10, 1889 in Monroe, Ohio. He attended Muskingum College in New Concord, Ohio (1912-1915), Antioch College in Yellow Springs, Ohio (1916-1918), and Xenia Theological Seminary in Xenia, Ohio (1915-1918) where he received his certification as a Presbyterian minister.
Warner assumed the pastorate of the United Presbyterian Church in Montrose, Colorado in July 1918. He remained the pastor of that congregation throughout his life, except during the years that he served as a chaplain in the U.S. Army during World War II. As a pastor, he was also active in missionary activities, and in promoting the welfare of Native Americans in Colorado.
Also active in promoting conservation, Warner was instrumental in having the Black Canyon region of Colorado declared a National Monument. The Black Canyon of the Gunnison River is located in western Colorado near the town of Montrose. The steep terrain and rocky rim area protected the Black Canyon from development during the 1800s. In 1928, an investigating committee headed by Warner, recommended that the Montrose Lions Club build a road to the canyon rim. The club began clearing ground in the Summer of 1929 while Warner campaigned to have the county aid in the road building activity.
The road was completed in the Fall of 1930, but well before that Warner and his committee were beginning to petition the National Park Service requesting the canyon be designated a national monument. After being rejected several times, the committee petitioned again in the Spring of 1932. The new Park Service director expressed an interest and a study was begun of the area. In the Fall of 1932, the Depression forced the Lions Club to disband and Warner immediately began to lobby the Montrose Chamber Of Commerce for their active support of the monument proposal.
The idea gained regional support in western Colorado. On the advice of Roger W. Toll of the Park Service, and with the assistance of local photographer Dexter Walker, Warner began to assemble information packets outlining the boundaries of the proposed monument and extolling its visual and geologic beauty. These packets were sent to members of the Park Service, Colorado's senators and representatives and other influential parties at the state and federal levels. Early in 1933, Colorado representative Edward T. Taylor became Warner's Washington advocate. He guided the petition through the Washington bureaucracy and by February 28, the Black Canyon Monument proclamation was approved. It was signed by President Hoover on March 22, 1933.
Warner remained actively involved with the Black Canyon Monument, serving on the local committee which provided input regarding the ongoing developments to the park. He wrote numerous articles about the history of the region and in 1967, with the help of Dexter Walker, wrote "Through The Black Canyon", a short book about the history of the canyon and the creation of the monument.
Mark Warner married Bertha Rich of Hamilton, Ohio on May 21, 1919. They had two children, Jeanne (born in 1922) and Robert (born in 1927).
The Mark T. Warner Papers (3 linear ft.) include correspondence with family members while serving as chaplain during World War II and other documents from his military service, including programs from services he performed during the war; papers accumulated from his career as Presbyterian minister in Colorado, especially notes from sermons; scattered papers of other, earlier family members; and papers relating to is efforts to have Black Canyon Monument established. The papers are organized into of five series: Personal; Chronological; Church Files, Military Files; and Black Canyon Monument.
Subjects:
Black Canyon of the Gunnison National Park (Colo.); Chaplains, Military.; Clergy--Colorado.; Colorado.; Presbyterian Church--Colorado.; United States. Army--Chaplains.; United States. National Park Service.; World War, 1939-1945--Chaplains.; Warner, Mark T. (Mark Thomas), 1889-1975.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Black Canyon of the Gunnison National Park (Colo.); Chaplains, Military.; Colorado.; Warner, Mark T. (Mark Thomas), 1889-1975.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Sermons.; Photographs.; Postcards.
- Personal Files 1813-1973
  The Personal Files (0.3 linear ft.) contains a miscellanea of personal and family documents. Included are scattered papers of Mark Warner's father, John Warner, as well as material documenting Mark Warner's activism on behalf of conservation and Native American welfare causes.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1928-1968 (Box 1)
  - Fishing data 1920-1924 (Box 1)
  - "The Indians of Colorado" by Mark Warner (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Monroe, Ohio (hometown) (Box 1)
  - Ouray Memorial Park 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Postcards (Box 1)
  - Speech (for a funeral) (Box 1)
  - United Presbyterian Theological Seminary 1914-1917 (Box 1)
    (include essays, etc.)
  - Warner, Bertha (wife) (Box 1)
  - Warner, John (father) 1813-1884 (Box 1)
- Chronological Files
  The Chronological Files (0.5 linear ft.) contain a mixture of correspondence and personal papers from various activities. Especially rich is the period during World War II when Warner wrote home to his family of his activities as an army chaplain.
  - 1909-1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1927 (Box 1)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1966 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1974 (Box 1)
- Church Files 1927-1958
  The Church Files (0.7 linear ft.) consists of subject files from Warner's career as a Presbyterian minister. Of some interest are his sermon notes, which contain insight into his thoughts about morality and scripture. The folder titled "missions" contains information on his desire to keep congregations in remote areas of Colorado open, despite a lack of funds, especially the mission at Telluride.
  - Book of Forms: Prayers for major events (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1928-1945 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Reports 1927-1935, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1917-1957 (Box 1)
  - Missions, primarily Telluride 1940-1958 (bulk 1948-1953) (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Presbytery, Western Colorado 1947-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Programs 1916-1951 (Box 1)
  - Sabbath School 1920-1926 (Box 1)
  - Sermon Notes, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - United Presbyterian Church
    - General 1919-1936 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, Member Lists, Constitution 1910-1943 (Box 2)
- Military Files 1928-1946
  The Military Series (0.5 linear ft.) contains a diary, photographs, correspondence from his superior officers, as well as programs from services he performed.
  - Church Services (Box 2)
  - Circular Letters from Chief of Chaplains (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (personal) 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Marriage Records 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (materials collected by MW during, and about, the war) (Box 2)
  - Monthly Report of Chaplains September 1940-April 1944 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of MW and other officers in uniform (Box 2)
  - Photos from South Pacific service (Box 2)
  - Office of the Corps Chaplains 1928-1945, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Notebook 1941-1946 (Box 2)
    (contains military records, orders, appointments, memoranda, etc.)
  - Diary, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    (includes transcripts)
- Black Canyon National Monument 1930-1967
  The Black Canyon Monument (1 linear ft.) series details Warner's efforts to protect and preserve this natural area of Colorado. The series is comprised of three subseries: Topical Files; Writings; and Photographs.
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files subseries pertains to the creation of the Black Canyon National Monument and subsequent modifications to the park area. Included is historical background and data about the parks creation and early operation. A correspondents list is included which identifies the authors and dates of the letters in the correspondence folders which follow. These contain letters showing how the monument was created, developed and administered. Included here are responses from National Park Service Directors Arno B. Cammerer and A.E. Demaray, United States Representative Edward Taylor, Colorado Governor Lee Knous and Herbert Hoover's secretary Lawrence Rickey. The correspondence written between 1929 and 1939 document the major period of Warner's activity. Also of note is the folder "Wilderness Proposal, 1970-1973" which documents, with maps, drawings and an environmental statement, the attempt to create a wilderness area within the perimeter of the park.
    - Attendance statistics 1930-1939 (incomplete) (Box 3)
    - Blueprints and landscaping designs 1934-1935 and master plan, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Descriptive data 1932 and diary, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Correspondents list (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1926-1939 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1940-1972 (incomplete) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and memos undated (Box 3)
    - Clippings 1930-1973 (Box 3)
    - Government brochures and publications 1925-1970 (Box 3)
    - Wilderness proposal 1970-1973
      - Proposal 1970 (includes the proposal, maps and notice of public hearings) (Box 3)
      - Environmental study 1973 (Box 3)
  - Writings
    The Writings subseries consists of publications and unpublished writings about the history and development of the canyon area which were written by Mark Warner and Dexter Walker. A bound copy of Through The Black Canyon, along with its drafts and other materials relating to its publication and sale are included. The remaining material in this series contains additional manuscripts and articles by Warner and Walker about the Black Canyon.
    - Through the Black Canyon file
      - Through the Black Canyon, 1972 published copy (Box 3)
      - Articles and research materials used to create Through the Black Canyon (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1957-1973 (Box 3)
      - Manuscript and notes undated (Box 3)
      - Legal and business papers 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - "Exploring the Black Canyon," (1916 manuscript of a newspaper article) (Box 3)
    - "Black Canyon of the Gunnison National Park," 1934 (Box 3)
    - "Through the Canyon," 1963 (Box 3)
    - "First Road to the Black Canyon," undated manuscript by Dexter Walker (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries include images taken in and around the Black Canyon. This material includes: photographs showing the construction and dedication of the rim road in 1930; early aerial views of the canyon; and color photos taken from the canyon rim.
    - Aerial views of the canyon undated (Box 3)
    - Building and dedication of the first road 1930 (Box 3)
    - Color photographs of the Black Canyon undated (Box 3)
    - Postcards of the region, 1959, undated (Box 3)